window.
Too late, someone thought of racing ahead and shutting the five-barred gate.
But in another moment, the van was through it and rapidly disappearing down the road.
Boxer was never seen again.
Three days later, it was announced that he had died in the hospital at Willingdon
in spite of receiving every attention a horse could have.
Squealer came to announce the news to the others.
He had, he said, been present during Boxer's last hours.
>> It was the most affecting sight I have ever seen, >> said Squealer, lifting his trotter and
wiping away a tear.
>> I was at his bedside at the very last, and at the end, almost too weak to
speak, he whispered in my ear that his sole sorrow was to have passed on before
the windmill was finished.
"Forward, comrades," he whispered.
"Forward in the name of the rebellion.
Long live Animal Farm. Long live Comrade Napoleon. Napoleon is always right."
Those were his very last words, comrades.
>> Here, Squealer's demeanor suddenly changed. He fell silent for a moment,
and his little eyes darted suspicious glances from side to side before he proceeded.
It had come to his knowledge, he said, that a foolish and wicked rumor had been
circulated at the time of Boxer's removal.
Some of the animals had noticed that the van which took Boxer away was marked
"horse slaughterer" and had actually jumped to the conclusion that Boxer was being sent to
the knackers.
It was almost unbelievable, said Squealer, that any animal could be so stupid.
"Surely," he cried indignantly, whisking his tail and skipping from side to side,
"surely they knew their beloved leader, Comrade Napoleon, better than that."
But the explanation was really very simple.
The van had previously been the property of the and had been bought by the veterinary
surgeon who had not yet painted the old name out.
That was how the mistake had arisen.
The animals were enormously relieved to hear this and when Squealer went on to
give further graphic details of Boxer's deathbed, the admirable care he had
received and the expensive medicines for which Napoleon had paid without a
thought as to the cost, their last doubts disappeared and the sorrow that they felt for their
comrade's death was tempered by the thought that at least he had died happy.
Napoleon himself appeared at the meeting on the following Sunday morning and
pronounced a short oration in Boxer's honor.
It had not been possible, he said, to bring back their lamented comrade's
remains for interment on the farm, but he had ordered a large wreath to be
made from the laurels in the farmhouse garden and sent down to be placed on Boxer's grave.
And in a few days time, the pigs intended to hold a memorial banquet in Boxer's honor.
Napoleon ended his speech with a reminder of Boxer's two favorite maxims.